Guide to the Robert D. Hess Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robert D. Hess papers
1949-1992
SC0460
Hess, Robert D.
65 Linear feet
Papers primarily pertain to Hess' research interests and include correspondence, lectures, articles, papers, reprints, project files, reports, and video and audio tapes; some files pertain to the cross-cultural study he conducted with Hiroshi Azuma of the University of Tokyo comparing the interaction of mothers and children in the United States and Japan. The papers also include records from his Chicago pre-school study.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Jared Hess, 1993; and transfer from the School of Education, Stanford, 1997.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Hess, a pioneer in the study of child development, held the Lee L. Jacks Professorship of Child Education at Stanford University. He received his a.b. at the University of California Berkeley in 1947 and his Ph.D. in human development from the University of Chicago in 1950. He taught at Chicago before joining the Stanford faculty.
Description of the Collection
Papers primarily pertain to Hess' research interests and include correspondence, lectures, articles, papers, reprints, project files, reports, and video and audio tapes; some files pertain to the cross-cultural study he conducted with Hiroshi Azuma of the University of Tokyo comparing the interaction of mothers and children in the United States and Japan. The papers also include records from his Chicago pre-school study, as well as audiorecordings.
Access Terms
Azuma, Hiroshi, 1926-; Hess, Robert D.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; Audiotapes.; Child development --Cross-cultural studies.; Child development --Research.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1997-188
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Original Data L 1-40 (Box 1)
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Original Data L 1-40 (cont’d.) (Box 2)
  - Interaction Protocols, Subjects 110-165 (Box 2)
  - Chicago Pre School Study (Box 3)
  - Interaction Protocols, Subjects 110-165 (cont’d.) (Box 3)
  - Misc. (Box 3)
  - Chicago Pre School Study Misc. (Box 4)
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Original Data (Box 5)
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Original Data (Box 6)
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Original Data, Interaction Protocols, Subjects 12-42 (Box 7)
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Follow Up Files, Interaction Protocols, Subjects 43-60 (Box 8)
  - Chicago Pre School Study, Follow Up Files (Box 9)
  - Tapes: Block Sort Game, Interaction Game - video, reel to reel; 2 video tapes for Helical Scan Video Recorder, reel to reel; Father Interviews, audio cassettes (Box 10)
  - Tapes: Mother Interviews, Father Interviews, Teacher Interviews, audio cassettes; 4 video tapes for Helical Scan Video Recorder, reel to reel (Box 11)
  - Tapes: Block Sort Game, Interaction Game (1973) - video, reel to reel (Box 12)
  - Tapes: Block Sort Game (1973) - video, reel to reel (Box 13)
  - Tapes: Block Sort Game (1973) - video, reel to reel (Box 14)
  - Tapes: Tower Building Telling How - video, reel to reel; Communication Game, Teacher Workshop Feedback Session, Teacher Interviews, audio cassettes (Box 15)
  - Tapes: Tower Building Telling How (1975-1976) - video, reel to reel (Box 16)
  - 5 audio cassettes (Box 16)
  - Tapes: Interaction Game (1973) - video, reel to reel; a few Tower Building Telling How - video, reel to reel (Box 17)
  - Tapes: Block Sort Game (1973) - video, reel to reel (Box 18)
  - Tapes: Unstructured Block Sort, Interaction Game (1973) - video, reel to reel (Box 19)
  - Chicago Pre School Study (Box 20)
  - Interaction Protocols, Subjects 61-109 (cont’d.) (Box 20)
  - Chicago Pre School Study (Box 21)
  - Original Data UL 1-42 (cont’d.) (Box 21)
  - Interactions Protocols, Subjects 61-109 (Box 21)
  - Chicago Pre School Study (Box 22)
  - Original Data UL 1-42 (Box 22)
- Audiorecordings, Accession ARCH-1998-052
  - Block Sort Game 5/16/73 (1057 DAD), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Block Sort Game 6/5/73 (1059 MA), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Block Sort Game 7/27/73 (1058 CC), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Block Sort Game 8/1/73 (1060 MP), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Unstructured/Block Sort Games 9/13/73 (2001 RE), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interaction/Block Sort 9/20/73 (2002 MH), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Interaction/Block Sort 9/20/73 (2003 RL), 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1066 (CS) Block Sort Game, 1973 Jun 4; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 1065 (JD) Block Sort Game, 1973 Aug 22; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 1067 (AC) Block Sort Game, 1973 May 30; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2013 (SB) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Nov 7; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 1064 (LT) Block Sort Game, 1973 Aug 7; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 1063 (JB) Block Sort Game, 1973 May 14; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 1062 (DD) Block Sort Game, 1973 May 9; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2010 (DG) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Sept 29; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2008 (PC) Unstructured/Block Sort Games, 1973 Oct 3; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2009 (ES) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Sept 26; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2005 (BB) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Sept 29; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2007 (KM) Unstructured/Block Sort Games, 1973 Oct 3; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2006 (MW) Unstructured Game/Block Sort, 1973 Sept 26; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2014 (SP) Unstructured/Block Sort Game, 1973 Oct 11; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 1061 (JC) Block Sort Game, 1973 Jul 30; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2015 (DS) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Oct 29; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 3)
  - 2004 (BT) Unstructured/Block Sort Games, 1973 Oct 3; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 4)
  - 2011 (GH) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Sept 26; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 4)
  - 2012 (RS) Unstructured/Block Sort, 1973 Nov 7; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 4)